<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Community Mapbuilder State Of Play - April 2006</title>

  <abstract>
    <para>This document summarises the state of the Mapbuilder project and
    it's relationship with projects around it, identify upcoming features and
    opportunities, and suggest where to focus future effort and funding to
    maximise Mapbuilder's potential.</para>

    <para>There has been a significant increase in developers downloading and
    extending Mapbuilder code. To maximise Mapbuilder's potential for
    developers, users and sponsors, the focus of core developers should move
    from development toward supporting and mentoring new developers.
    Similarly, sponsors should dedicate part of their funds to Mapbuilder
    mentors. <emphasis role="bold">Sponsor one mentor and you get five
    developers for free</emphasis>.</para>
  </abstract>

  <section>
    <title>What is Mapbuilder?</title>

    <para>Mapbuilder is a modern, web based geographic mapping client. It's
    modular design has made it easy for developers to build an every
    increasing library of widgets and tools to plug into Mapbuilder. In
    particular, Mapbuilder stands out from other Webmapping clients because it
    allows users to draw vector features on a map then load the feature into a
    Transactional Web Feature Service.</para>

    <para>Mapbuilder is built upon OGC standards and hence is interoperable
    with many other Geospatial applications.</para>

    <para>Mapbuilder has grown a strong, diverse and active developer
    community and as Mapbuilder reaches it's 1.0 release it is being
    recognised as a quality product. Mapbuilder is bundled with Geoserver, an
    Open Source Web Map Service (WMS) and Transactional Web Feature Service
    (WFS), and Mapbuilder was selected as one of the founding projects for
    OSGeo, the Open Source Geospatial Foundation.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>What big ticket items are in the pipeline?</title>

    <section>
      <title>Geographic wiki</title>

      <para>Web Mapping to date has focused on Publishing mapping data.
      Feature entry functionality is being added to Mapbuilder which will
      allow users to create, edit, then upload geographic features.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Integrated Suite of Open Source Mapping products</title>

      <para>There is a full range of high quality open source geospatial
      software which interacts which each other using Open Standards - however
      the installation and configuration of these products is still
      disjointed. Over the next few years, these projects are likely to
      integrate more closely providing easy to install and configure
      solutions.</para>

      <para>In particular, Mapbuilder is currently bundled with Geoserver, an
      open source WFS/WMS, and there is an opportunity for Mapbuilder to be
      bundled with Udig to provide a heavy/light client solution.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Roll your own Webmapping Client</title>

      <para>Imagine a web page which looked like a drawing program like Visio.
      On the left is a list of widgets which can be dragged onto a Pane on the
      right. After the user has selected and placed their widgets, the use can
      assign attributes like Map Layers.</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://www.netvibes.com/">http://www.netvibes.com/</ulink> uses a
      similar concept which made it very popular.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>AJAX drawing tool</title>

      <para>Mapbuilder has developed effective drawing functionality which
      would be useful for a wide range of applications. This should be
      factored out into a separate library so that it can be used by other
      applications.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Lots of extra widgets and features</title>

      <para>Google and Yahoo Map layers, fast vector rendering of features (eg
      using SVG), tiled maps, and much more.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Managing growth</title>

    <figure>
      <title></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="emailsFeb06.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Over the last year Mapbuilder has had a steady increase in interest
    from developers and users. Traffic on our email lists has increased by a
    factor of five over the last year. Increasingly we are seeing questions
    from paid portal developers who extend Mapbuilder, then move on. Since
    most core developers work on Mapbuilder in their spare time the core
    developers are having problems supporting users and incorporating the
    user's code.</para>

    <para>Almost all Mapbuilder queries are from developers, which is an
    indication that Mapbuilder documentation and installation procedures are
    too difficult for average internet users.</para>

    <para>Mapbuilder's user documentation is still poor which is part of the
    reason for the large number of user queries. Improving documentation will
    empower users to answer their own queries, and will increase Mapbuilder's
    user base because more people will be able to use it.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Funding</title>

    <para>Mapbuilder has grown to privileged position where we are starting to
    have access to more developers than the core team can support. To accept
    developer contributions, we need to provide guidance, answer technical
    questions, review code and incorporate additions into the code base. Part
    of the support can be provided by writing good supporting
    documentation.</para>

    <para>If you are considering using or extending Mapbuilder, sponsoring a
    Mapbuilder mentor will probably make sense for you. <emphasis
    role="bold">Sponsor one mentor and get five developers for
    free.</emphasis> For a company who wants to extend Mapbuilder, I suggest
    you hire a developer to implement your desired features and a mentor for
    1/5 of your developer's time. This will ensure your code is reviewed and
    incorporated into the Mapbuilder codebase and available in future
    Mapbuilder releases. If your desired functionality is popular, it may be
    more economical to just support a Mapbuilder mentor which in turn will
    empower other Mapbuilder developers to implement features on your
    behalf.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Integrating with projects around us</title>

    <para>The commercial world regularly tries to out do and compete against
    similar projects, but in Open Source we can do much better by embracing
    and working together.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Web mapping clients</title>

      <para>There are a number of web mapping clients doing similar things to
      Mapbuilder or with features that Mapbuilder would like to copy. The
      projects all contain talented software developers and we would all do
      better if we could share our workload and focus on one great product
      instead of lots of good products.</para>

      <para>Unfortunately it is difficult to merge two code bases together and
      no one wants to give up a project they have spent lots of time on to go
      and work on someone else's code.</para>

      <para>So what I propose is that we work toward a long term goal of
      merging projects. We start by gradually factoring out common libraries
      that we work on together, and whenever we make future design decisions,
      we run the idea past other projects and see if we reuse code or
      interfaces which will ease merging some time in the future. <ulink
      url="webmap-discuss-subscribe@mail.osgeo.org">webmap-discuss@lists.osgeo.org</ulink>
      has been set up to facilitate this.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>OpenStreetMap and other Geowikis</title>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://www.openstreetmap.org/ ">http://www.openstreetmap.org/</ulink>
      is a project which allows users to upload tracks from GPS devices (like
      handheld computers or phones) into a geographic database, then provides
      a java applet to edit those same features. They have addresses some of
      the hard issues, like version control on features at the expense of
      breaking away from Open Standards. And they are already collecting data
      from users.</para>

      <para>This is a project that would be great to work with. They have a
      great vision, and some good ideas. We could add value to them by
      providing our AJAX based web mapping client - they have a Java applet.
      Java applets are a stumbling block for many non-technical users because
      it requires them to download and install extra software into their
      browser. We could help them migrate toward a standards based solution,
      which would enable them to tap into other powerful mapping applications
      (like UDig).</para>

      <para>There has been talk on Wikipedia about setting up a geographic
      wiki. Mapbuilder could be the tool used for a Wikipedia for geographic
      maps.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Basemap providers</title>

      <para>There has been an explosion of quality free basemaps on the
      internet from companies like Google, Yahoo, and MSN. These companies
      also provide viewers which could be seen as competitors to Mapbuilder.
      These companies could be seen as potential sponsors for the Mapbuilder
      project as their code value is in their maps, not the mapping
      client.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>AJAX Engines</title>

      <para>Mapbuilder has built it's own AJAX software - (software which
      handles asynchronous loading, events, javascript inheritance etc). It is
      powerful, and it works, however some of the code is not very elegant,
      and because we were experimenting as we wrote it, we have instances
      where concepts like inheritance are implemented in two different ways.
      This makes the code harder to understand and more prone to bugs.</para>

      <para>Since we wrote Mapbuilder, there have been a number of quality
      AJAX Engines written. It would be wise of Mapbuilder to replace our
      engine with one of the dedicated engines. The advantages would be: more
      reliable code, maintenance would be spread across a larger user base and
      we can tap into the expertise of the developers on these
      projects.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Geoserver</title>

      <para>Geoserver is a Java based Transactional Web Feature Service
      (WFS-T) and Web Map Service. Mapbuilder is currently bundled with
      Geoserver which probably explains why a number of our quality developers
      have been attracted to Mapbuilder.</para>

      <para>We need to ensure that Mapbuilder continues to be bundled with
      Geoserver and ensure that Geoserver ships with the latest version of
      Mapbuilder.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>UDig</title>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://udig.refractions.net/confluence/display/UDIG/Home">UDig</ulink>
      is a powerful GIS desktop application. It would be very useful for users
      to bundle Mapbuilder with UDig to provide a light/heavy client
      option.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Open Web Services Testbed (OWS4)</title>

      <para>The OWS4 testbed sponsored by the Open Geospatial Consortium would
      be an excellent opportunity to show case Mapbuilder and UDig
      integration.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Areas for improvement</title>

    <section>
      <title>Documentation</title>

      <para>Mapbuilder's documentation needs to catch up to the quality of the
      code. By improving our documentation, we won't need to keep answering
      the same questions on email lists and will increase our user base.
      Increased users, means increased developers and sponsorship and a
      healthier project.</para>

      <para>The catch is that the people who know the most about the code (the
      developers) don't need the documentation and sponsors often want to pay
      for a feature and move on. Good documentation is a long term investment
      in a project.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Testing</title>

      <para>It is a credit to the Mapbuilder team that Mapbuilder is so stable
      considering that it targets the flaky browser platforms.</para>

      <para>To date Mapbuilder has only just started looking at automated
      testing, however it has not been rolled out across the project.
      Automated testing will help ensure Mapbuilder remains stable and give us
      confidence to take on more developers.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Core code</title>

      <para>Mapbuilder's code has gone through many improvements as we have
      pioneered and experimented with AJAX techniques. As such there are areas
      of code which still contain old hacks and plenty of areas where we could
      simplify code. This would reduce download size, reduce complexity and
      improve maintainability.</para>

      <para>We should do a systematic code review and clean up and improve our
      existing core code, and replace some of our code with standard AJAX
      libraries.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Managing new developers and funding</title>

      <para>We have become overwhelmed with new developers and their
      questions. This is a good thing, but we do need to change the way we do
      things. In particular, the core team needs to focus more on Mentoring
      new developers. Ideally, sponsors should consider sponsoring a
      Mapbuilder mentor. Sponsor one mentor, get five developers for
      free.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Visibility</title>

      <para>To build the project's profile, we should present Mapbuilder at
      various conferences.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>